EPISODE 10
ODCINEK 10
This is your fault, Mirei.
To twoja wina, Mirei.
What?
Co?
It's your fault that Ayaka disappeared!
Przez ciebie Ayaka zniknęła!
I just thought
Myślałam,
that she needed to confess
że jeśli się przyzna,
what she had done to save everyone.
to wszystkich uratuje.
But we haven't been saved.
Ale nie udało się.
That's...
To...
All you did was make Ayaka vanish
Przez ciebie Ayaka zniknęła,
because you told us to remember stuff!
bo kazałaś nam sobie przypominać!
-Memi, you're wrong! -I'm not wrong!
- Mylisz się, Memi! - To nieprawda!
I told you! I have been telling you!
Mówiłam wam! Mówiłam!
If we remember, we will disappear! I said we shouldn't try to remember!
Kiedy sobie przypominamy, znikamy! Dlatego przestańmy to robić!
But the Hemingway novel...
Ale powieść Hemingwaya...
-That doesn't matter! -Memi!
- To nie ma znaczenia! - Memi!
Take responsibility for causing everyone to disappear!
Weź odpowiedzialność za ich zniknięcie!
We could have saved Ayaka,
Mogłyśmy ocalić Ayakę,
but Mirei kept pressuring her.
ale Mirei na nią naciskała.
We need to remember the past.
Musimy przypomnieć sobie przeszłość.
Who cares about that?
Po co?
Hey.
Hej.
You should say something, Kyoko.
Powiedz coś, Kyoko.
It's all Mirei's fault!
To wszystko wina Mirei!
I remember what you said.
Pamiętam, co powiedziałaś.
You said we should disappear.
Że powinnyśmy zniknąć.
Wait. Listen to me.
Czekaj. Posłuchaj mnie.
You said the two of us should disappear!
Powiedziałaś, że obie powinnyśmy zniknąć!
Calm down, Kyoko.
Uspokój się, Kyoko.
Quit acting innocent!
Nie udawaj niewinnej!
I'm not the one who made Ayaka disappear!
To nie przeze mnie Ayaka zniknęła!
"Remember!"
„Przypomnijcie sobie!”
You were trying to frame me and Ayaka!
Chciałaś wrobić mnie i Ayakę!
I was only doing what I think is right to save all of us.
Chciałam nas uratować.
I told you to quit trying to escape blame!
Przestań uciekać przed odpowiedzialnością!
But if we don't do this,
Ale jeśli nic nie zrobimy,
is there any other way that we can be saved?
jak mamy się uratować?
If Ayaka is dead, none of this is worth anything!
Jeśli Ayaka nie żyje, nic już się nie liczy!
Kyoko.
Kyoko.
I was only making a vague promise
Ja tylko tak sobie mówiłam...
when I said, "Let's live together after graduating."
o tym wspólnym mieszkaniu po zakończeniu szkoły.
But she remembered.
Ale ona pamiętała.
People always said that I talk and act like a guy.
Ludzie zawsze mówią, że zachowuję się jak facet.
Ever since entering high school, I have been teased about it.
Słyszałam to przez całe liceum.
But then,
A potem...
she was the first person who ever called me pretty.
ona jako pierwsza nazwała mnie ładną.
I apologize.
Przepraszam.
I did Perfect stuff on my own.
Sama działałam w ramach Idealnej.
Because I entrapped those men,
Szantażowałam tych facetów
I ended up getting Miho's dad in trouble.
i sprowadziłam problemy na ojca Miho.
But that happened because of what I started.
Wszystko to zdarzyło się przeze mnie...
It wasn't Ayaka's idea.
nie przez Ayakę.
If you think it was our fault that everyone started bullying Miho,
Jeśli uważasz, że Miho nękano przez nas...
then all the blame should be on me.
zrzuć całą winę na mnie.
I apologize.
Przepraszam.
I apologize for all of it.
Przepraszam za wszystko.
Please, Mirei.
Proszę, Mirei.
Give Ayaka back to me!
Oddaj mi Ayakę!
Kyoko!
Kyoko!
"Remember"? You planned to make us all vanish from the start!
„Przypomnijcie sobie”? Od początku planowałaś nasze zniknięcie.
No, I didn't!
To nieprawda!
I just want to get out of here!
Chciałam tylko się stąd wydostać!
Everyone...
Wszystkie...
Everyone is going to disappear.
Wszystkie znikniemy.
Why's it getting so hot?
Czemu tu się robi tak gorąco?
Kumi.
Kumi.
What?
Co?
Can you remember anything else about Miho's dad?
Pamiętasz coś jeszcze o ojcu Miho?
Not that again! I've had enough with that!
Tylko nie to! Mam tego dość!
Shut up!
Zamknij się!
That's our only chance.
To nasza jedyna szansa.
Are you going to vanish Kumi next?
Teraz pozbędziesz się Kumi?
Kumi,
Kumi,
will you trust me?
zaufasz mi?
Kumi, don't do it. Don't listen to her!
Nie rób tego, Kumi. Nie słuchaj jej!
Mirei,
Mirei...
do you still think that Miho's dad is behind this?
myślisz, że za tym wszystkim stoi ojciec Miho?
-Kumi! -Well...
- Kumi! - Ja...
The message we got is very clear.
Dostałyśmy jasną wiadomość.
"Remember Miho's dad."
Miałyśmy przypomnieć sobie ojca Miho.
I told you we shouldn't remember!
Nie powinnyśmy!
That stuff Mr. Hayashi said was a trap for sure!
Pan Hayashi nas nabrał!
A trap?
Co?
He told us to remember,
Kazał nam sobie przypomnieć,
but he only said it because they forced him to.
ale tylko dlatego, że go zmusili.
It was all a trap!
To był podstęp!
If we doubt that, where do we stop?
Skoro tak, co robimy?
Can you prove it wasn't a trap?
Masz dowód, że to podstęp?
Well, no.
Nie.
You may look smart, Mirei, but you are actually pretty dumb.
Wyglądasz na inteligentną, Mirei, ale jesteś głupia.
You are always just making stuff up.
Zawsze coś wymyślasz.
I'm doing this for everyone!
Robię to dla nas wszystkich!
Cut it out!
Przestańcie!
Try to understand, Kumi.
Zrozum, Kumi.
Mirei has lost her mind trying to save herself.
Mirei zwariowała, próbując się uratować.
You are wrong.
Mylisz się.
Mirei is just trying to think of ways to help all of us.
Mirei chce nam pomóc.
You are on Mirei's side?
Jesteś po jej stronie?
I want to survive!
Chcę przeżyć!
You do too, right, Memi?
Ty też, prawda, Memi?
Mirei,
Mirei.
I don't think Miho's dad is behind this.
Nie wydaje mi się, by za tym stał ojciec Miho.
Why?
Dlaczego?
I have thought about this stuff.
Zastanawiałam się nad tym.
Miho's dad wouldn't want people to know about the medical error.
Ojciec Miho nie chciałby, żeby ludzie dowiedzieli się o błędzie medycznym.
Yes, that's true.
To prawda.
Clearly, this medical equipment
Ten sprzęt medyczny
is meant to make us remember the medical error.
na pewno ma nam o nim przypomnieć.
So, it wouldn't make any sense at all for Miho's dad to do this.
Ojciec Miho jako sprawca? To nie ma sensu.
But...
To...
Then what is the meaning of this post on Perfect?
o co chodziło z tym wpisem na Idealnej?
Yes. That's a good question.
Dobre pytanie.
Not an earthquake again! How many times will this happen?
Znowu to trzęsienie ziemi! Ile jeszcze ich będzie?
Hey! Don't start looking around again and tell us to remember stuff!
Przestań się rozglądać i nie każ nam niczego sobie przypominać!
That's our only choice.
Nie mamy innego wyboru.
Cut it out!
Przestań!
Do you want to sacrifice someone else again?
Znowu chcesz kogoś poświęcić?
Mirei,
Mirei,
tell me what you are thinking.
powiedz, o czym myślisz.
For example,
To mógł być
-it could be another teacher... -These two have lost their minds.
- inny nauczyciel... - Obie zwariowały.
I'm the only one
Tylko ja tu...
who is thinking straight.
jasno myślę.
That teacher acted arrogant, but he wouldn't hurt a fly.
Pan Fujiwara zachowywał się arogancko, ale był nieszkodliwy.
He could never do anything as outrageous as this.
Nie zrobiłby nam czegoś takiego.
Kumi.
Kumi.
-Kumi! -What?
- Kumi! - Co?
What about Miho's mom?
A mama Miho?
Well...
Ona...
She died when Miho was little.
umarła, kiedy Miho była mała.
I see.
Rozumiem.
At any rate, there's no doubt that someone is watching us.
W każdym razie ktoś na pewno nas teraz obserwuje.
I'm certain of that.
Tego jestem pewna.
It's one of us.
To jedna z nas.
That's the only possibility.
To jedyne rozwiązanie.
Memi?
Memi?
The culprit behind this is among us.
Jedna z nas stoi za tym wszystkim.
It's one of us!
To jedna z nas!
One of you is lying!
Jedna z nas kłamie!
-What has gotten into you? -That's the only possibility!
- Co w ciebie wstąpiło? - To jedyne rozwiązanie!
No, it isn't!
Nieprawda!
-Why? -Well...
- Dlaczego? - Bo...
If that were true, Mr. Hayashi's actions wouldn't make sense.
gdyby tak było, zachowanie pana Hayashiego nie miałoby sensu.
Not him again!
Nie mówmy już o nim!
You mean, when he tried to destroy the stuffed head?
Mówisz o tym, gdy próbował zniszczyć wypchaną głowę?
That's right.
Tak.
He was trying to do something for us.
Chciał nam pomóc
He vanished because of that.
i dlatego zniknął.
There is a camera in its eye.
W oku głowy jest kamera.
That's why Mr. Hayashi tried to destroy it.
Dlatego pan Hayashi próbował ją zniszczyć.
Even if there's really a camera in it,
Nawet jeśli faktycznie jest tam kamera,
there is no way to be sure that somebody is watching through it.
nie wiemy, czy ktoś nas przez nią obserwuje.
Maybe nobody's watching at all.
Może wcale nie.
Then there's no reason to put a camera, right?
Po co ktoś miałby tam wstawiać kamerę?
Yes, there is.
Ja widzę powód.
If there's a camera...
Kamera
then naturally, we will believe that the culprit is outside this room.
każe nam myśleć, że sprawca jest poza tym pomieszczeniem.
But actually, it's one of us.
A tak naprawdę to jedna z nas.
I mean, if they really want to watch us suffer,
Gdyby naprawdę chcieli obserwować nasze cierpienie,
the best view would be from inside this room.
najlepszy widok mieliby z tego pokoju.
Why do you want to believe so badly that one of us is responsible?
Czemu tak bardzo chcesz uwierzyć, że to dzieło jednej z nas?
When we were all still here,
Kiedy jeszcze...
you are the one who brought up what we all had in common.
wszystkie tu byłyśmy, powiedziałaś, że mamy coś wspólnego.
You mean, that we're the ones who bullied Miho?
Że wszystkie dręczyłyśmy Miho?
Right.
Tak.
You said it, right, Mirei?
Powiedziałaś tak, prawda?
You said we all bullied Miho.
Powiedziałaś, że dręczyłyśmy Miho.
For example,
Na przykład...
Me and Mana both wrote graffiti on Miho's desk
Mana i ja pisałyśmy graffiti na jej ławce
and threw cleaning rags on her lunch.
i rzucałyśmy brudne ścierki na jej lunch.
I wonder what Kyoko and the others did.
Ciekawe, co robiła Kyoko i reszta.
Come to think of it, Sarina said
Sarina powiedziała,
Kyoko was going to cut Miho's face with some broken glass.
że Kyoko chciała pociąć twarz Miho rozbitym szkłem.
She broke a bottle,
Rozbiła butelkę
-and tried to make it look like... -Kumi.
- i chciała... - Kumi.
You never directly bullied Miho, did you?
Ty nie skrzywdziłaś Miho, prawda?
Right. But I never tried to save her either.
Nie, ale też nie próbowałam jej ratować.
Back then, I always took my break times in the library or on the roof.
Wtedy zawsze na przerwie chodziłam do biblioteki albo na dach.
Miho texted me a lot, but I always ignored her.
Miho często do mnie pisała, ale ją ignorowałam.
Because you didn't want to be involved in the bullying?
Dlatego, że nie chciałaś jej dręczyć?
That's what it looks like, doesn't it?
Tak to wygląda, prawda?
Actually, I wanted her to realize the bad things she did.
Chciałam, żeby zrozumiała, że źle postępuje
I wanted her to remember that wasn't Perfect's original purpose.
i że nie o to chodziło w Idealnej.
I just wanted her to know that.
Chciałam, żeby to wiedziała.
Next, it's your turn, Mirei.
Twoja kolej, Mirei.
How did you bully Miho?
Co zrobiłaś Miho?
I did the same as Kumi.
To samo co Kumi.
I turned a blind eye to the bullying that went on.
Udawałam, że nie widzę, jak się nad nią znęcacie.
That's it?
To wszystko?
I knew that everyone was bullying Miho, but I didn't do anything about it.
Wiedziałam, co jej robicie, ale nie reagowałam.
So, you yourself didn't do anything, Mirei?
Czyli sama nic jej nie zrobiłaś?
But, that's the same as Kumi, right?
Tak samo jak Kumi, prawda?
The meaning is totally different.
Wcale nie.
I mean, Kumi was friends with Miho since they were little.
Kumi przyjaźniła się z Miho od dziecka.
They have always been best friends.
Były najlepszymi przyjaciółkami.
Hey.
Hej.
Why didn't you do any bullying, Mirei?
Mirei, czemu nie nękałaś Miho?
Because that kind of thing is stupid.
Bo to głupie.
If that's what you thought, you could have stopped it.
Skoro tak, mogłaś nas powstrzymać.
But...
Ale...
I knew everyone wanted to get revenge on Miho.
wiedziałam, że wszyscy chcą się na niej zemścić.
Hypocrite!
Hipokrytka!
Actually, you held us in contempt, didn't you?
Gardziłaś nami, prawda?
No, I didn't.
Nie.
Anyway, that's not what I want to know.
Ale nie to mnie interesuje.
Come on.
Daj spokój.
You must have had some other reason.
Musiałaś mieć jakiś powód.
Are you suspecting me?
Podejrzewasz mnie?
You are the one who suspected everyone else.
Ty podejrzewasz wszystkich.
All I did was say that we should all pay for the crimes we committed.
Powiedziałam tylko, że musimy zapłacić za swoje grzechy.
Doesn't she seem far away?
Czemu ona jest tak daleko?
What?
Co?
I wonder why only Mirei is so far away.
Czemu tylko Mirei siedzi tak daleko?
I guess it's because...
Chyba specjalnie.
Even if we found out she's responsible for this,
Żebyśmy nie mogły jej nic zrobić,
nobody will be able to do anything to her.
kiedy zrozumiemy, że to jej sprawka.
It's pure chance I'm over here.
To przypadek.
That's right. You are going too far.
To prawda, przesadzasz.
Mirei was...
Mirei...
desperate to become the number one at our school.
bardzo chciała być najlepsza w szkole.
You were friends with Sarina,
Przyjaźniłaś się z Sariną,
but when she did better than you, you got hostile with her.
ale kiedy stała się od ciebie lepsza, zaczęłaś traktować ją jak wroga.
What's the point of getting revenge before graduation just for that?
Po co miałaby mścić się za coś takiego zaraz przed zakończeniem?
Hey, Memi, at the very least,
Memi...
all the stuff we remembered was about Miho.
wszystko, co sobie przypomniałyśmy, dotyczyło Miho.
Everything in this room and everything that has appeared,
Wszystko w tym pokoju i rzeczy, które się pojawiały,
they were all related to Miho.
mają związek z Miho.
Do you think that's a coincidence?
Myślisz, że to przypadek?
Okazaki, Miho's Dad,
To może być sprawka Okazakiego, ojca Miho,
or
nawet...
maybe even I could be behind this.
moja.
But Mirei has no motive.
Ale Mirei nie ma motywu.
What about the sisters?
A siostry?
What?
Co?
Maybe Miho has a sister.
Może Miho ma siostrę.
You mean, the talk about Miho's dad having an illegitimate child?
Chodzi o te plotki, że ojciec Miho ma nieślubne dziecko?
That's just a rumor from a gossip magazine.
To bzdury z plotkarskiego magazynu.
Once,
Kiedyś
I talked to Mr. Hayashi about Miho's family.
rozmawiałam o rodzinie Miho z panem Hayashim.
I jokingly said,
Zażartowałam sobie,
"They are so rich. They probably have an illegitimate child."
że tacy bogacze pewnie mają nieślubne dzieci.
Mr. Hayashi suddenly got a serious look on his face.
Pan Hayashi nagle spoważniał
He said, "Don't make rash remarks like that."
i powiedział, że mam tak nie mówić.
He just didn't want you to spread such awful rumors.
Nie chciał, żebyś plotkowała.
No, that's not it.
Nie o to chodzi.
I'm sure he meant that he didn't want me to tell anyone in the class.
Nie chciał, żebym mówiła o tym w klasie.
That's because
Bo siostra Miho...
her sister is in the same class.
też w niej była.
Just because you said that?
Bo ty tak powiedziałaś?
I get it now!
Już rozumiem!
Mirei was bought.
Pan Hayashi i Mirei
Mr. Hayashi and Mirei were both bought by the Watanabe family.
zostali przekupieni przez rodzinę Watanabe.
Even though Miho's dad fell from power,
Nawet po stracie władzy
he still has that hospital, right?
ojciec Miho dalej ma szpital, prawda?
He must still have a lot of money.
Musi nadal być bogaty.
You think I got rid of my classmates for money?
Myślisz, że pozbywam się koleżanek dla pieniędzy?
You are jumping to conclusions.
To pochopny wniosek.
Be honest, Mirei. Your family is poor, right?
Przyznaj się, Mirei. Twoja rodzina jest biedna, prawda?
That's so stupid.
Co za bzdury.
No matter how much I was given, it would never be worth it.
Żadna suma pieniędzy nie byłaby tego warta.
Are you sure?
Jesteś tego pewna?
I would be happy to make that much money.
Ja bym chętnie trochę zarobiła.
I remember now!
Już pamiętam!
Cut it out!
Przestań!
When I woke up,
Kiedy się obudziłam,
everyone else was asleep, but Mirei was the only one awake.
tylko Mirei nie spała.
-What? -I'm sure of it!
- Co? - Jestem tego pewna!
I thought I was the second one, but I wasn't.
Myślałam, że obudziłam się jako druga, ale teraz wiem,
Mirei was awake in here the whole time.
że Mirei w ogóle nie spała.
She has been watching us the whole time!
Cały czas nas obserwowała!
You are wrong! I was put to sleep too.
Mylisz się! Mnie też uśpiono!
Mirei is the one who kept telling us to remember stuff!
Mirei kazała nam sobie wszystko przypominać!
She's doing it to make us confess to what we did to Miho!
Chciała, żebyśmy się przyznały, co zrobiłyśmy Miho!
No, I didn't!
To nieprawda!
Bring them back! Bring everyone back!
Sprowadź je z powrotem!
How can I make you understand?
Jak mam was przekonać?
You are playing innocent again!
Znowu udajesz niewinną!
Mirei,
Mirei,
if you want to prove your innocence, then remember something yourself.
jeśli chcesz udowodnić swoją niewinność, sama sobie coś przypomnij.
-Isn't there anything? -I already told you!
- Cokolwiek. - Już mówiłam!
I turned a blind eye to everyone's bullying.
Ignorowałam to, że dręczycie Miho.
-Would you still be here for doing that? -How should I know?
- To dlaczego ciągle tu jesteś? - Skąd mam wiedzieć?
Everyone else has disappeared.
Pozostałe dziewczyny zniknęły.
Ask whoever is behind this.
Spytajcie sprawcę.
Stop it.
Przestań.
Stop it!
Przestań!
You did all this!
To twoja sprawka!
You are the one responsible!
To ty za tym stoisz!
You did all this to get revenge for Miho!
To twoja zemsta za Miho!
If I'm wrong, then prove it!
Udowodnij mi, że się mylę!
You did it, and you know it!
Wiesz, że to twoja sprawka!
Say something!
Powiedz coś!
That is called Devil's Proof.
Na to się mówi diabelski dowód.
That's right! You are the devil!
To prawda, jesteś diabłem!
Memi,
Memi,
stop it.
przestań.
Why?
Dlaczego?
Don't tell me you are in on this too.
Też jesteś w to zamieszania?
Are you the devil's friend?
Przyjaźnisz się z diabłem?
Memi.
Memi.
I was finally going to graduate.
Nareszcie miałam skończyć szkołę.
I was finally going to escape my annoying father and live on my own!
W końcu miałam uciec od denerwującego ojca i zamieszkać sama.
I was going to have a boyfriend,
Chciałam mieć chłopaka
and I was going to have all kinds of fun!
i dobrze się bawić!
There was nothing for me during high school.
Liceum było dla mnie beznadziejne.
There wasn't a single good thing!
Nic dobrego mnie tak nie spotkało.
-Memi... -Shut up!
- Memi... - Zamknij się!
Let me go right now!
Wypuść mnie stąd!
You are the one behind this! You know it!
To twoja sprawka! Dobrze o tym wiesz!
Fine. I'll tell you just like you want me to.
W porządku. Powiem to.
That's right.
To prawda.
I was the first one to bully Miho.
Ja zaczęłam dręczyć Miho.
What?
Co?
Miho always treated me like her slave.
Zrobiła ze mnie swojego niewolnika.
Thanks to that, everyone else treated me the same.
Przez to wszyscy mnie tak traktowali.
I did all the class's chores.
Wszystkie klasowe obowiązki spadły na mnie.
"Do this!" "Buy that!"
„Zrób to!" „Kup tamto!"
That's all I ever heard!
Ciągle tylko te rozkazy!
I hated it!
Miałam tego dość!
After what happened to Miho's dad,
Po tym, co zdarzyło się ojcu Miho,
I thought I wouldn't have to fear her anymore.
pomyślałam, że nie muszę już się jej bać.
That's why I started rumors.
Dlatego zaczęłam rozpuszczać plotki.
I said Mao made fun of Miho.
Powiedziałam, że Mao wyśmiewa Miho,
I said Shiho kicked Miho in the back.
a Shiho kopnęła ją w plecy.
You did that?
To twoja wina?
How about it, Mirei?
Co ty na to, Mirei?
Are you satisfied now?
Zadowolona?
Are you satisfied now that you know who the mastermind is?
Cieszysz się, że już wiesz, kto za tym stał?
Why should I care? I told you, I'm not the one behind this.
Co mnie to obchodzi? Mówiłam, że nie ja to robię.
See, Mirei?
Widzisz, Mirei?
I remembered.
Przypomniałam sobie coś.
Please!
Proszę!
I'm begging you!
Błagam!
Make me disappear now!
Pozwól mi zniknąć!
Mirei, please!
Proszę, Mirei!
You are behind this, right?
Ty za tym stoisz, prawda?
You can get rid of us anytime you want, right?
Możesz pozbyć się nas wszystkich w każdej chwili, prawda?
Please!
Proszę!
Tell me I'm right!
Powiedz, że mam rację!
If you don't, then what will happen to me?
Bo jeśli nie, to co ze mną będzie?
Will I have to stay in this room forever?
Mam tu zostać na zawsze?
Do I have to stay here until I die?
Aż do śmierci?
Please!
Proszę!
I'll apologize!
Przepraszam!
I'm the one responsible for starting the bullying.
To ja zaczęłam dręczyć Miho!
Come on!
Proszę!
I'm begging you, please!
Błagam cię!
I'm begging you!
Błagam!
Yes! I did it!
Tak! To ja!
Finally...
Nareszcie...
THIS DRAMA IS A WORK OF FICTION.
PRZEDSTAWIONY SERIAL JEST FIKCJĄ.
Subtitle translation by Brian Athey
Napisy: Arianna Sugier